PETER SZOLOVITS: So
last time we talked
about what medicine
does, and today I
want to take a deep
dive into medical data.
And I'm going to use as examples
a lot of stuff from the MIMIC
database, which is
one of the databases
that we're going to be
using in this class.
Some of you are probably
familiar with it,
and some of you are not.
And there are, I hope,
some takeaway lessons
from this discussion.
So for example, a
few years ago, when
MIMIC-III was about
to be released,
I was playing with
the data, and I
looked at the distribution
of heart rates
in the CareVue part
of the database.
So MIMIC, for those
of you who don't know,
has intensive care data from
about 60-something thousand
admissions to intensive care
units at the Beth Israel
Deaconess Medical Center over
a period of about 12 years.
And one of the
technical difficulties
that we encountered is that in
the middle of that time period.
The hospitals shifted from
one information system
that they used in their
intensive care unit to another.
CareVue is the old one.
MetaVision is the new one.
And of course, they're
not exactly compatible.
So we'll see some
examples of that.
So this is the old data.
So this is from CareVue.
And you look at that and
say, well, heart rates
range from 40 to 200
roughly, which is OK.
But then there's
this funny thing.
There are two peaks.
So where, if ever,
do you see two peaks
in physiological data?
Not typical.
And so my initial reaction was--
[LAUGHTER]
So then I looked
a little closer,
and I said, hmm, what
do the heart rates look
like from these two systems?
And if you look in CareVue,
you see the picture
that I just showed you.
And if you look
in MetaVision, you
see this other picture,
which looks more like what
you would normally expect.
And so I'm sitting there
scratching my head going,
OK, there must be some
difference between these.
It's not that simultaneous
with the switchover
of the hospital from one
information system to another.
Physiology of people
changed, and all
of a sudden some
subset of people
started having
faster heart rates.
Right?
But if you think about
that what subset of people
have faster heart rates?
AUDIENCE: Athletes.
PETER SZOLOVITS: Hmm?
AUDIENCE: Babies?
AUDIENCE: If you're
in a stress test.
PETER SZOLOVITS: Unh-hmm.
AUDIENCE: Is it children?
PETER SZOLOVITS: Yeah, kids.
So I said, hmm, interesting.
So anyway, if you look
at the statistics,
you see that the mean heart
rate in CareVue is 108,
and the mean heart rate
in MetaVision is 87.
But of course, means
are not that meaningful
when you look at these
bimodal distributions.
So then I said, well, what
if we just look at adults?
So we look at people from age
greater than 1 up to age 90.
And I'll say a word
about that in a minute.
And I look at those
two distributions.
They look pretty close.
They look pretty similar.
So that means that
the number of patients
of different ages
in the adult group
is similar in the two data sets.
But if I don't exclude the
very young or the very old,
then I see this
funny distribution
where I have suppressed
ages greater than 90
but not the young.
And what you see is
that in CareVue there's
this giant spike at age 0.
So what happened at the hospital
is that under the old system
it was also being used in the
NICU, the Neonatal Intensive
Care Unit.
And the new system was not
being used in the NICU.
And therefore, they didn't
capture data about babies.
And in fact, if you
look at age versus heart
rate of the entire
population, you
see two very peculiar things.
So here are the adults that
we've been talking about,
and here are the babies.
And sure enough, they
have higher heart rates.
And then here are these
300-year-old people.
[LAUGHTER]
You go, wow, I don't think I'm
going to have a heart rate when
I'm 300 years old.
So who are those people?
Anybody have a clue?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Entry errors.
PETER SZOLOVITS: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: Entry errors?
PETER SZOLOVITS: There
are too many of them.
Yeah, entry errors is
always a possibility,
but there's quite a
few data points there.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PETER SZOLOVITS: Close.
It's not quite missing data.
So HIPAA, the Health Insurance
Portability and Accountability
Act, defines a set of
criteria about protecting
personal health information.
And one of the things
you are not allowed to do
is to specify the
age of somebody
who is 90 years old or older.
And the reason is because
the number of 97-year-olds
is pretty small.
And so if I tell you that
Willy is 97 years old,
then you're going to be able
to pick him out of a population
relatively easily, and so
it's prohibited to say that.
So as a result, everybody
who's 90 or older
gets labeled as being 300
years old in the database.
It's an artifact.
It's like back in my youth, I
worked as a computer programmer
at a health sciences
computing facility at UCLA.
And we used to have a
convention that missing data was
represented by 99999.
And of course, if you average
that into a real data set,
you get garbage, which
people did regularly.
So there are problems
with this, and we're
running into one of those.
If you look at just the
adults, the two systems
actually look very similar.
So the blue and red
dots, or the two systems,
and I've drawn the trend
lines between them,
and you can see that
they're very similar.
So it looks like
as you get older,
your heart rate
declines very slightly.
But it does so equally
in the two data sets.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: On the previous
slide, beyond 300,
it looks like they're
older than 300?
PETER SZOLOVITS: Well that's
because the ages there
are computed at the time that
the heart rate is measured.
And so if you are
300 years old when
you're admitted to
the hospital, if you
stay in the hospital
for six months,
then you're 300
and 1/2 years old
by the time of that measurement.
[LAUGHS] So that's why
there are data points
to the right of 300.
Yeah, good catch.
OK, and then this is what
the babies look like.
And of course, they do
have higher heart rates.
And here here are the oldsters.
So actually, there are
people out to 310 years
old because maybe they were
discharged from the hospital.
And then at age
100, they came back.
You know, maybe they
were 90 years old
at the time they were initially
admitted 10 years later.
They came back, and we
recorded more data about them,
and so this is all
relative to that 300.
OK, so that's just one example.
And the lesson
there is be careful
when you look at data because
it can really easily fool
you 'cause there are all kinds
of funny things about the way
it's collected, about
these artifactual things
like 300-year-old
patients and so on.
So here's a catalog
of the types of data
that are available to us.
So we have the typical kind of
electronic health record data
from hospitals--
demographics, age, sex,
socioeconomic status,
insurance type, language,
religion, living situation,
family structure,
location, work, et cetera.
We have vital signs--
your weight, your height,
your pulse, respiration rate,
body temperature, et cetera.
So these are
typically the things
that if you ever go
to a doctor's office,
or you go into a
hospital, the nurse
will take you aside and weigh
you and measure your height
and check your blood pressure
and take your temperature
and stuff like that.
These are standard
vital signs, and so we
have lots of those recorded.
Medications--
prescription medications,
over-the-counter
drugs, illegal drugs
if you're willing not to
lie to your health care
provider, alcohol.
Again, one of my
earliest days, I
was hanging out with a
cardiologist at Tufts Medical
Center, and we see
this elderly lady
who looks kind of terrible.
And we're talking to her--
well, the doctor
is talking to her.
I'm trying to stay
out of the way.
And he says, so do
you drink alcohol?
And she says, oh, no,
never touch the stuff.
And then we talk some
more, and we go out
of the patient's room.
And the doctor turns to me
out of earshot of the patient
and says, oh, she's
a chronic drunk.
I said, well, how do you know?
And he says, well,
from lab tests,
from the appearance of her
skin, from her general demeanor,
from various sort of
ineffable factors.
And so patients lie.
They really do because they
don't want to tell you things.
Medications, by the
way, is a big deal.
So there is this whole field
called med red, medication
reconciliation, which is the
hospitals or the doctors'
offices attempt to figure
out what medications
you're actually taking.
So I'm a member of
the MIT health plan,
and if I sign into my
health plan account,
it tells me that I'm
taking some pills that I
got 12 years ago as part
of a laboratory test,
where I took two pills
which were supposed
to have some
physiological effect,
and then they measured that.
And I've never
gotten another pill
and never taken one
since then, nor would it
be particularly good for me.
But it's still on my
record, and there's
no notice of it ever
having been discontinued.
And that's a real
problem because if you're
taking care of a
patient, you'd like
to understand what drugs
they're actually taking,
and it's hard to know.
Then lab tests-- so
this is the things
that you imagine
that we do a lot of,
and these are components of
the blood and the urine mainly,
but also of the stool, saliva,
spinal fluid, fluid taken off
the belly, joint fluid,
bone marrow, stuff
coming out of your lungs.
It's anything and
any place where
you can produce
some specimen, they
can send it to a lab and
measure things in it,
and they measure lots and lots
of different kinds of things.
And these are often useful.
Pathology, qualitative and
quantitative examination
of any body tissue, for
example, biopsy samples
or surgical scraps.
You know, if they
do an operation,
they cut something out
of you, that typically
winds up on a
pathologist's bench,
who then tries to figure out
what its characteristics are
and that's, again,
useful information.
Microbiology--
ever since Pasteur,
we know that organisms
cause disease.
And so we're quite interested
in knowing what organisms
are growing inside your body.
And typically, testing is not
only to identify the organism
but also to figure
out which antibiotics
it's sensitive to
and insensitive to.
And so you'll see things like
reports of sensitivity testing
at various dilutions.
In other words, they try
to give a strong dose
of an antibiotic a
week weaker dose a week
or dose a weaker
dose a week or dose
to see which is the
minimum level of dosing
that's enough to
kill the bacteria.
There's a comma missing there,
but input, output of fluids
is another important thing
because people, especially
in the hospital, often get
either dehydrated or over
hydrated.
And neither of those
is good for you,
and so trying to keep track
of what's going into you
and what's coming out
of you is important.
Then there are tons of notes.
So an important one that we're
going to look at in this class
is discharge summaries.
So these are the
typically long notes
that are written at the
end of a hospitalization.
So this is a summary of why you
came in, what they did to you,
the main things they
discovered about you,
and then plans for what to
do after your discharge.
Where are you going to go?
What drugs are you
going to be taking?
When are you supposed to come
back for follow up, et cetera.
I'll show you an excruciatingly
long one of those
later in the lecture today.
But we also have notes from
attendings and/or residents,
nurses, various
specialties, consultants.
The referring physician--
if somebody sends you
to the hospital, that
doctor will usually
write a note saying this
is what I'm interested in.
Here's why I'm sending
in the patient.
There are letters back to the
referring physician saying, OK,
this is what we found out.
Here's the answer to the
question you were asking.
There are emergency
department notes.
So that's often the first
contact between the patient
and the health care system.
So these are all important.
And then there's tons
and tons of billing data.
So remember the EHR
systems were initially
designed by accountants.
And they were designed for
the purpose of billing.
And so we capture a lot of
data about formalized ways
of describing the
condition of the patient
and what was done to
the patient in order
to submit the right bills.
You obviously want to bill
through it as much as possible.
But you have to be able to
justify the bills that you
submit because insurance
companies and Medicare
and Medicaid don't have
a good sense of humor.
And if you submit bills for
things that you can't justify,
then you get penalized.
And then there are
administrative data
like, which service are you on?
So this this is occasionally
a confusing thing.
You can go into the hospital
and have heart problems,
but it turns out that
the heart intensive care
unit, the cardiac intensive care
unit, is full up with patients.
But there's an extra bed in the
pulmonary intensive care unit,
and so they stick
you in that unit,
but you're still on
the cardiology service.
And so there are these sort of
mixture kinds of cases that you
still have to take care of.
Transfers are when you get
transferred from one place
to another in the hospital.
Imaging data-- so I'm not going
to talk about that much today,
but there are X-rays,
ultrasound, CT, MRI, PET scans,
retinal scans, endoscopy,
photographs of your skin
and stuff like that.
So this is all imaging
data, and there's
been a tremendous
amount of progress
recently in applying
machine learning
techniques to try to interpret
the contents of these data.
So these are also
very important.
And then there's the whole
quantified self movement.
I mean, how many of you
where an activity tracker?
Only about 1/3?
I'm surprised at
a place like MIT.
[LAUGHTER]
So you know, we measure
steps and elevation change
and workouts.
And you can record
vital signs and diet
and your blood sugar,
especially if you're diabetic;
allergies, allergic incidents.
There's all this mindfulness,
mood, sleep, pain,
sexual activity.
And then people have
developed this idea
of N of 1 experiments.
For example, I had
a student some years
ago who suffered from psoriasis.
It's a grody
condition of the skin.
And the problem is there
are no good cures for it.
And so people who
suffer from psoriasis
try all kinds of things.
You know, they stop
eating nonce for a while,
or they douse
themselves with vinegar.
Or they do whatever crazy
thing comes to mind.
And we don't have a good theory
for how to treat this disease.
But on the other hand, some
things work for some people.
And so there's a
whole methodology that
has been developed that says,
when you try these things,
act like a scientist.
Have hypotheses.
Take good notes.
Collect good data.
Be cognizant of things
like onset periods, where
you know you may have to drip
vinegar on yourself for a week
before you see any effect.
So if that doesn't do a thing
after one day, don't stop.
And furthermore, if you stop
then don't start something new
immediately because
you will then
be confused about whether this
is the effect of the thing
you were on before or the
new thing that you're trying.
So there's all sorts
of ideas like that.
So this is a slide from
our paper on MIMIC-III.
And it gives you a kind
of overview of what's
going on with the patient.
So if you look at this--
I'm going to point
with my hands--
at the top is something
very important.
This patient starts
off at full code.
That means that if something
bad happens to him,
he wants everything to be
done to try to save him.
And he winds up in
comfort measures
only, which means that if
something bad happens to him,
he wants to die--
or his family does
if he's unconscious.
So what else do we
know about this guy?
Well GCS is the
Glasgow Coma Score.
And it's a way of
quantifying people's level
of consciousness.
And you see that
at the beginning
this patient is oriented,
and then gets confused.
And finally, is only making
incomprehensible words
or sounds.
Motor, he's able
to obey commands.
Eventually, he's
only able to flex
when you stimulate his muscles.
So he's no longer conscious.
Eye movements-- he's able
to follow you spontaneously.
He's able to orient to speech.
And eventually
orientation at all.
So this is clearly somebody
who's going downhill quickly
and, in fact, dies at
the end of this episode.
Now, we then look
at labs so we can
see what is their level of
platelets at about the time
that they're measured,
their creatinine level,
their white blood cell count,
the neutrophils percentage, et
cetera.
And there's not every possible
data point on the slide.
This is just illustrative.
The next section is medications.
So the person is on morphine.
They're on Vancomycin,
which is an antibiotic.
Piperacillin-- I don't
know what that is.
Does somebody know?
AUDIENCE: Antibiotic.
PETER SZOLOVITS: It's what?
AUDIENCE: It's antibiotic.
PETER SZOLOVITS: OK.
Sodium chloride 9%, So that's
just keeping him hydrated.
Amiodarone and dextrose.
So dextrose is giving
him some energy.
And then these are the
various measurements.
So you see the heart rate,
for example, is up pretty high
and is going up near the end.
The oxygen saturation
starts off pretty good.
But here we're
down to 60% or 50%
O2 sat, which is supposed
to be above about 92
in order to be
considered reasonable.
So again, this is a
very consistent picture
of things going very badly wrong
for this particular patient.
So this is all the
data in the database.
Now, if you want to try to
analyze some of this stuff,
you can say, well,
let's look at the ages
at the time of the last lab
measurement in the database.
So we have the times of
all the lab measurements.
So we can see that many of the
ICU population are fairly old.
There's a relatively small
number of young people
and then a growing number of
older people in both females
and males.
If we look at age at
admission by gender--
so this is age at admission not
age at the time the last lab
measurement was done--
it's a pretty similar curve.
So we see that
females were 64.21
at time of last lab measurement;
63.5 at the time of admission.
So we can look at demographics,
and demographics typically
includes these kinds of factors,
which I've mentioned before.
And again, if we're
interested in the relationship
between this and, for
example, the age distribution,
we see that if you look at the
different admission types--
so you can be either
admitted for an emergency
for some urgent
care or electively.
And it doesn't seem to make
a whole lot of difference,
at least in the means of the
population age distribution.
On the other hand, if you
look at insurance type
and, say, who's
paying the bills,
there is a big difference
in the age distributions.
Now, why do you think that
private insurance drops way off
at about 65?
AUDIENCE: Isn't insurance
always covered for everyone
by the state health?
PETER SZOLOVITS: It's
because of Medicare.
So Medicare covers people
who are 65 years old.
There's a terrible story
I have to tell you.
I was talking to somebody at
an insurance company who's
a bit cynical, and
he said suppose
that you see a 63-year-old
patient who's developing type
2 diabetes, what
should you do for him?
Well, there are
standard things you
should do for
somebody developing
type 2 diabetes, like get
him to eat better, get
him to lose weight, get
him to exercise more,
et cetera, et cetera.
But his cynical answer
was absolutely nothing.
Why?
Well it's very
cheap to do nothing.
Most people who
develop type 2 diabetes
don't get real sick
in the next two years.
And by the time
this patient is 65,
he'll be the government's
responsibility,
not the insurance company's.
Nice.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PETER SZOLOVITS: So of
course a lot of the elderly
are insured by Medicare or
Medicaid, not that surprising.
Self-pay is a
pretty small number
because it's insanely expensive
to pay for your own health
care.
What about where you came from?
Were you referred
from a clinic, or were
you an emergency room admit?
Or were you referred
from an HMO or et cetera?
And other than a transfer from
a skilled nursing facility
or transfer within the
facility, within the hospital,
it doesn't make much difference.
The averages there
and the distributions
look moderately similar.
If you're coming from a
skilled nursing facility,
if you are in a skilled
nursing facility,
you're probably old because
younger people don't typically
need skilled nursing care.
And I'm not sure why
transfers within the facility
are significantly
younger ages, but that's
true from the MIMIC data.
What about age at
admission by language?
So some people speak English.
Some people speak not available.
Some people speak
Spanish, et cetera.
So it turns out the
Russians are the oldest.
And that may have to do
with immigration patterns,
or I don't know exactly why.
But that's what the data show.
If you do it by
ethnicity, it turns out
that African-Americans,
on the whole,
are somewhat
younger than whites.
And Hispanics are
somewhat younger yet.
So that means that those
subpopulations apparently
need intensive care earlier
in life than whites.
So this is a topic that's
very hot right now,
discussions about how bias
might play into health care.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: What does
unable to obtain mean?
PETER SZOLOVITS: It
just means that somebody
refused to say what
their ethnicity was.
AUDIENCE: When they
were asked this?
PETER SZOLOVITS: Yeah.
I think.
I'm not positive.
AUDIENCE: So just to confirm.
This also represents Boston's
population dynamics too, right?
PETER SZOLOVITS: It's
the catchment basin
of the Beth Israel
Deaconess Hospital,
which is Boston clearly.
But there are-- it turns out
that a lot of North Shore
people go to Mass General, and
so different hospitals have
different catchment basins.
AUDIENCE: Does it have anything
to do with like, is this just
the ICU?
Or is this everybody who goes
to the hospital or the ER?
PETER SZOLOVITS: These are
all people who at some point
were in the ICU.
So these are the
sicker patients.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So just
want to double-check
there's a higher proportion of
black, African American people
in the population here as
well because the red is
higher than the others?
PETER SZOLOVITS: No, actually--
I don't remember if
I have that graph--
I think this is cumulative.
AUDIENCE: Oh, OK.
PETER SZOLOVITS:
So most people are
white for whatever definition
of white we're using.
And I think it's only the
increment that you see on top.
All right, how about
marital status?
Well, according to this,
it's bad to be single.
So I could sort of see
that for hospitalization.
I'm not sure why
it's true for the ICU
because if you don't have
anybody at home to take care
of you when you get
sick, it seems reasonable
that you'd be more likely
to wind up in the hospital.
But I don't know why you'd
wind up in intensive care.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Isn't it possible
that those are also
single people are probably
younger than married people,
and those are probably
younger than--
PETER SZOLOVITS: Yes, yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] people.
PETER SZOLOVITS: Yeah,
that's probably also right.
So here's an
interesting question,
a little bit related
to something you'll
see on the next problem set.
So could we predict
in-hospital mortality
from just these
demographic features?
So I'm using a tool
in language called
R. This is a general
linear model,
and I've set it up to do
basically logistic regression.
And it says I'm
predicting whether you
die in the hospital based on
these demographic factors.
And it turns out that
the only ones that
are highly significant are age.
So that's not surprising,
that older people
are more likely to die
than younger people.
It's generally true.
And if I'm unable to
obtain your ethnicity,
or I don't know your ethnicity,
then you're more likely to die.
I have no clue why
that might be the case.
And other things are
not as significant.
So if you speak
Spanish or English,
you're slightly
less likely to die.
You see a negative
contribution here.
And if you speak Russian, you're
slightly less likely to die.
But it's significant not
at the p equal 0.05 level,
but it is at the p
equal 0.06 level.
And marriage doesn't seem
to make much difference
in predicting whether
you're going to die or not.
Now, remember, this
is ICU patients.
And we're looking at
in-hospital mortality.
AUDIENCE: For
ethnicity, can they
learn that at any
point in this study,
or just right at the beginning?
Or do you know?
Because I don't know.
PROFESSOR: I don't know.
AUDIENCE: Because
it could be that
unable to obtain means that they
died before we can ask them.
PROFESSOR: No,
because there wouldn't
be that many of those
people, I think.
There are not that
many people who don't
live past the intake interview.
And they do ask them.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yeah, that
would be an example.
But I don't think you'd see
enough such people to show up
statistically.
OK.
Well, so I've already
mentioned that there
is this problem of having
moved from CareVue view
to MetaVision just in
the MIMIC database.
But of course, this is
a much bigger problem
around the country
and around the world,
because every hospital has its
own way of keeping records.
And wouldn't it be nice
if we had standards?
And of course, there's
this funny phrase,
the wonderful thing
about standards
is that there's so
many to choose from.
So for example, if you look
at prescriptions in the MIMIC
database, here are two
particular prescriptions
for subject number
57139 admitted
on admission ID 155470.
And so they have the same start
date but different end dates.
One is a prescription for
Tylenol, acetaminophen,
and the other is for clobetasol
propionate 0.05% cream.
That's a skin lotion thing for--
I think it's a
steroid skin cream.
So if you look in
the BI's database,
they have their own
private formulary
code where this thing is
acet325 and this thing
is clob.05C30, right?
And if you look,
there there's also
something called a GSN, which
is some commercial coding
system for drugs.
Maybe having to do with
who their drug supplier is
at the hospital.
And these have different codes.
There's the National Drug Code,
which is an FDA assigned nine
digit code that specifies who
made the drug, what form it's
in, and what's its strength.
And so you get these.
Then there's a human
readable description
that says Tylenol comes
in 325 milligram tablets.
And the clobetasol
comes in 30 gram tubes.
And the dose is supposed
to be 325 to 650, i.e. one
to two tablets
measured in milligrams.
The dose here is one
application, whatever that is.
I don't know what
the 0.01 means.
And this is a tablet
and that's a tube.
And this is taken orally.
That's administered
on the skin, right?
So this is a local database.
AUDIENCE: For a doctor,
they just [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: At most
hospitals, that's true now.
It wasn't true when
the MIMIC database
started being collected.
And the BI was
relatively late in moving
to that compared to some of the
other hospitals in the Boston
area.
Each hospital has
its own digitorata
for what it thinks
is most important.
And I think the BI just didn't
prioritize it as much as some
of the other hospitals.
OK, so then I said, well, if
you look at prescriptions,
how often are they given?
So remember, we have
about 60,000 ICU stays.
And so iso-osmotic dextrose
was given 87,000 times
to various people.
Sodium chloride
0.9 percent flush.
Do you know what that is?
Have you ever had an IV?
So periodically,
the nurse comes by
and squirts a little
bit of stuff in the IV
to make sure that it
hasn't clogged up.
That's what that is.
Insulin, SW.
I don't know.
Salt water?
I don't know what SW is.
Magnesium sulfate,
dextrose five in water.
Furosimide is a diuretic.
Potassium chloride
replenishes potassium
that people are often low on.
And then you go, so why is
there this D5W and that D5W?
And that's probably some
data in the system, OK?
One of them has an NDC
code associated with it
and the other one doesn't
but probably should.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: I was actually
going to ask, does yours mean
that they're standard
across hospitals
or just that we
don't have the data?
PROFESSOR: The NDC code should
be standard across the country,
because those are
FDA assigned codes.
But not every hospital
uses them, OK?
And for the ones
that say zero, I'm
not sure why they're
not associated
with a code in this
hospital's database.
OK, next most common,
you see normal saline,
0.9 percent sodium chloride.
So that was the same stuff
as the flush solution
but this time not
being used for flush.
Metoprolol is a beta blocker.
Here's another insulin this time
with an NDC code, et cetera.
I love bag and vial, OK?
So these are not
exactly medications.
A bag is literally like a baggy
that they put something into,
and a vial is
literally something
that they put pills in.
And why is that in the database?
Because they get to
charge for it, OK?
And I don't know
what the charge is,
but it wouldn't
surprise me if you're
paying $5 for a plastic
bag to put something in.
OK, so if we say, well, how
many pharmacy orders are there
per admission at this hospital,
and the answer is a lot.
So if you look at--
it's a very long
tailed distribution,
goes out to about 2,500.
But you see, if I blow up just
the numbers up to about 200,
there's a very large
number of people
with two prescriptions filled,
and then a fairly declining
number with more.
And then it's a very long tail.
So can you imagine 2,500
things prescribed for you
during a hospital stay?
Well, a little more
about standards,
so NDC is probably the
best of the coding systems.
And it's developed by the FDA.
The picture up on
the top right shows
that the first four digits
are the so-called labeler.
That's usually the person
who produced the drugs,
or at least the person
who distributes them.
The second four digit number
is the form of the drug,
so whether it's capsules, or
tablets, or liquid, or whatever
and the dose.
And then the last two digits
are a package code which
translates into the total number
of doses that are in a package,
right?
So this is a godsend.
And all of the robotic
pharmacies and so on
rely on using this kind
of information nowadays.
Unfortunately, they ran
out of four digit numbers,
and so there's now a--
they added an extra digit,
but they didn't do it
systematically, and
so sometimes they
added an extra
digit to the labeler
and sometimes to
the product code.
And so there is a
nightmare of translations
between the old codes
and the new codes.
And you have to have a
code dictionary in order
to do it properly and so on.
OK, well, if that
weren't good enough,
the International Council
for the Harmonization
of Technical requirements for
Pharmaceuticals for Human Use
developed another coding
system called MedDRA, which
is also used in various places.
And this is an
international standard,
which is, of course,
incompatible with the NDC.
CPT is the Common Procedural
Terminology, which we'll
talk about in a little bit.
And they have a
subrange of their codes
which also correspond to
medication administration.
And so this is yet another way
of coding giving medicines.
And then the HCPCS
is yet another set
of codes for specifying
what medicines
you've given to somebody.
And then I had mentioned this
GSN number, which apparently
the Beth Israel uses.
This as a commercial coding
system from a company
called First Databank
that is in the business
of trying to produce standards.
But in this case,
they're producing
ones that are pretty redundant
with other existing standards.
But nevertheless, for
historical reasons,
or for whatever reasons,
people are using these.
OK, enough of drugs.
So what procedures
were done to a patient?
If you look in MIMIC,
there are three tables.
There's procedures ICD, which
has ICD-9 codes for about
a quarter million procedures.
There's CPT events, which
has about half a million,
600,000 events that are
coded in the CPT terminology.
And then MetaVision, the
newer of the two systems,
has about a quarter
million procedure events
that are coded in that system.
So some examples, here's the
most common ICD-9 procedure
codes.
So ICD-9 code 3893 of which
there are 14,000 instances
is venous catheterization,
not elsewhere classified.
So what's venous
catheterization?
It's when somebody sticks
an IV in your vein, OK?
Very common.
You show up at a hospital.
Before they ask you your name,
they stick an IV in your arm.
That's a billable event, too.
Then insertion of an
endotracheal tube,
you know, if you're having
any problems like that,
they stick something
down your throat.
Ventral infusion of concentrated
nutritional substances,
so if you're not able
to eat, then they
feed you through a
stomach tube, OK?
So that's what that is.
Continuous invasive
mechanical ventilation
for less than 96
consecutive hours,
so this is being put
on a ventilator that's
breathing for you, et cetera.
So you see that there is
a very long tail of these.
So those are the ICD-9 codes.
Now, CPT has its
own procedure codes
that go into a tremendous
amount of detail.
So for example, this is
the medicine subsection,
and it shows you
the kinds of drugs
that you're being
administered that
are involved in dialysis,
or psychiatry, or vaccines,
or whatever.
And then here are the surgical
and the radiological codes.
And there's tons and
tons of detail on these.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So how can they put
these codes as 1,000 to 1,022?
This is really
annoying for anyone--
PROFESSOR: No, these
are categories.
So if you drill down,
there's a fanout of that tree
and you get down to
individual codes.
Just as a nasty surprise, CPT
is owned by the American College
of Physicians, and
they could sue me
if I showed you the actual codes
because they're copyrighted.
And you have to pay them
if you use those codes.
It's crazy.
OK, so if you look
at the number of all
of these codes
per admission, you
see a distribution like this.
Or if I separate
them out, you see
that there are more ICD-9
codes and fewer of the CPT
and the codes that
are in MetaVision.
But they look somewhat similar
in their distributions.
OK, lab measurements.
So you send off a sputum
sample, blood, urine,
piece of your brain, something.
They stick it in some goo and
measure something about it.
So what is it that
they're measuring?
Well, it turns out
that hematocrit
is the most common measurement.
So this is how much
hemoglobin is in your blood,
or what fraction in your
blood, and is very important
for sick people.
And the second most
important is potassium,
then sodium creatinine,
chloride, urea nitrogen,
bicarbonate, et cetera.
So this is a long, long
list of different things
that can be measured, and all
the stuff is in the database.
So for example, here's patient
number two in the database.
And on July 17 of 2138, this
is part of the deidentification
process to make it
difficult to figure out
who the patient actually is.
This person got a
test for their blood
and they reported
atypical lymphocytes.
So there are a couple
of interesting things
to note here.
One is that some things have
a value and others don't.
So this is a
qualitative measure,
so there's no value
associated with it.
Just the fact of the label tells
you what the result of the test
was.
The other thing
that's interesting
is this last column,
which is LOINK,
and I'll say a word
about that in a minute--
actually right now.
So LOINK is the Logical
Observation Identifiers Names
and Codes.
It was developed
by our colleagues
at Regenstrief Clinic in Indiana
about 15 years ago, maybe 20
years ago at this point.
And the attempt was to say every
different type of laboratory
test ought to have
a unique name,
and they ought to
be hierarchical
so that if you have, for
example, three different ways
of measuring serum
potassium, that they're
related to each other
but that they're
distinct from each
other, because there may
be circumstances under
which the errors that you
get from one measurement
versus another are different.
And so this is the standard way.
If you send off your
blood sample to a lab,
they send back a string
like this to the hospital
or to your doctor's
office that says,
it's coded in this
OBX coding system,
and here is the
LOINK code, and this
is the SNOMED interpretation.
And so this string is the
way that your hospital's EHR
or your doctor's office
system figures out what
the result of the test was.
HL7 is this 30-something
year old organization
that has been working on
standardizing stuff like this.
And LOINK is part of
their standardization.
So if you look at these,
you say, well, again,
how many tests per admission?
Again, a huge, long
tail up to about 15,000
for a very small
number of patients.
If you look at lab
tests per admission,
you can do a log
transform and get
something that looks like a
more reasonable distribution.
By the way, that's a very
generic lesson when we're
going to do analyses
of these data, is that,
often, doing a transform of some
sort, like in this case, a log,
takes some funny
looking distribution
and turns it into something
that looks plausibly
normal, which is better for a
lot of the techniques we use.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
means the same thing?
Like, for instance--
PROFESSOR: Yes.
AUDIENCE: --hematocrit
[INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Yes
AUDIENCE: --same?
AUDIENCE: Always same?
PROFESSOR: Yes, that's the whole
idea of creating the standard.
And that has been pretty
successful, pretty
successfully adopted.
OK, chart events.
So these are the things
that nurses typically
enter at the bedside.
And so there are 5.1,
5.2 million heart rates
measured in the MIMIC database.
And calprevslig is an artifact.
It exists in every record.
And it's some calibration
something or other
that doesn't mean anything.
I've never been able to
figure out exactly what it is.
SPO2 is the partial pressure
of oxygen in your blood.
If you use a pulse oximeter,
that's what that's measuring.
Respiratory rate, heart rhythm,
ectopy type, dot, dot, dot.
Now, you might be troubled
by the fact that here
is heart rate again, right?
But I've already shown you
this, that heart rate in CareVue
and heart rate in
MetaVision were
coded under different
codes in the joint system
that we created out of
those two databases.
And so you have to take
care of figuring out
what's what if you're
trying to analyze this data.
Not only do we have that problem
of different age distributions
across the two
different data sets,
but we also just have
the mechanical problem
that there will be things with
the same label that may or may
not represent the same
measurement at different times
in the system.
OK, this is the number of chart
entries per admission, again,
on a log scale.
So you see that
there are about 10
to the 3.5 chart entries
per admission, so thousands
of admissions, of chart
events per admission.
We also track outputs.
So Foley catheter
allows your bladder
to drain without your
having consciously
to go to the bathroom, so
they collect that information.
There are 1.9 million recordings
of how much fluid came out
of your bladder.
Chest tubes will drain
stuff out of your chest
if you have congestion.
Urine is if you pee regularly,
stool out, et cetera.
And again, I'm not
sure I understand
what the difference is between
urine out Foley versus Foley.
They may be the
same thing but one
from CareVue and
one from MetaVision,
so again, typical
kinds of problems.
If you look at the number of
output events per admission,
you're seeing on the
order of 100, roughly.
Well, if you're
tracking outputs,
you should also track
inputs, and so they do.
And so D5W is this dextrose
in water, 0.9 percent
normal saline.
Propofol is an anesthetic.
Insulin, heparin, blood
thinner, et cetera.
Fentanyl is, I think, an
opioid, if I remember right.
So these are various things
that are given to people.
And they affect the
volume of the person.
So this is an attempt to
keep the person in balance
and keep track of that.
MetaVision inputs are
classified somewhat differently
but they have similar
kinds of data.
And if you combine
them, you get, again,
a distribution on
a log scale that
shows that there are
on the order of 10
to the fifth input
events, so quite
a few input events, because
this is recorded periodically.
Now, the paper that I--
yeah.
AUDIENCE: What's
the input again?
Is that when you come to the
hospital and get admitted or--
PROFESSOR: No, no, no.
It's an input into you.
So it's like you drink
a glass of water,
the nurse is supposed
to record it.
Although, she doesn't always
because she may not notice it.
But if they hang an IV bag
and pour a liter of liquid
into you, they do
record that, OK?
All right, so I had you
read this interesting paper
and a discussion
prior to that paper,
because one of the authors
is a former student of mine.
And I know one of the
other guys pretty well.
And the former
student, Zak Kohane,
came back some years ago from
a conference in California
and was explaining to me
that he ran into a venture
capitalist who
discovered that there
is an interesting physiological
variation in the abnormality
of lab tests that
are done at night.
And he suspected that there
was a diurnal variation
that lab tests actually
become more abnormal at night
than they do during the day.
And Zak, who is not only a
computer science PhD but also
a practicing doctor,
turns to him and says,
you're an idiot, right?
Who has their blood drawn
at 3 o'clock in the morning.
It's typically not
healthy people, right?
So this is another of these
nice confounding stories
where, if you have a test done
in the middle of the night,
it probably indicates
that you're sicker.
So he and Griffin recruited
their third author
and went off and did
a very large scale
study of this question, which
is what the paper that I
asked you to read reports on.
And so I said,
well, I wonder if I
could reproduce that study
in the MIMIC database.
And the answer, just in
case you get your hopes up,
was no, in large part
because we just don't
have the right kind of data.
So there are not
that many white blood
counts that were measured in
the MIMIC database, for example.
But if you look at the--
this is MIMIC data.
And if you say,
what's the fraction
of abnormal white blood
count values by hour--
so this is midnight to midnight.
And each hour, there's some
fraction of these test results
that are abnormal.
And sure enough, what you
see is that, at 5 o'clock
in the morning, a much
higher fraction of them
is abnormal than at 3
o'clock in the afternoon,
OK, which is consistent with
Zak's peremptory comment
about the guy being an idiot.
So once again, I
said, well, can we
build a really simple
model that predicts
who's going to die in the
hospital in this case?
That's the easiest
one to predict
because I have that data.
We could get three-year
survival data, which
is what they were looking at.
But it's harder and it runs
into censoring problems
of what happens if the
person was hospitalized
less than three years before
the end of our data collection
period and so on.
And so I avoided that.
But what this is showing you
is, for each of the hours,
zero to 24, what is the
number of measurements?
And for each of
those hours, what
is the fraction of those
measurements that's
abnormal, OK?
So I said, well,
let's just throw it
into a logistic
regression model.
And what comes out is
something really weird,
which is that a few particular
hours are significant,
but most of them are not.
And that looks like
noise to me, right?
Because you wouldn't
expect that, at 8 o'clock
in the morning, the fact that
you had something measured
matters.
But at 9 o'clock in the
morning, it doesn't.
That doesn't seem sensible.
So I don't think there's
enough signal here.
And in fact, when I looked at
the number of white blood count
measurements at night and
related to mortality--
so false means people lived
and true means they died.
But you see that there's not
a whole lot of difference
between the distributions.
But you also see that the
number of white blood counts
is relatively small
in this database.
And so I think we just don't
have enough data to do it.
On the other hand, if you look
at a panel of different drugs,
you look at mean values of
blood urea nitrogen or calcium
chloride, CO2, et cetera,
you see that there
is variation across time.
So there is some
sort of variance
that's either caused by
the diurnal physiology
of the human body or by the
routine practice of medicine,
about when people choose
to take lab measurements.
And in fact, if you look at the
fraction of high end low lab
values, they do vary by hour.
And in particular, if you
look at white blood counts,
you see that the fraction of
high values goes up at night
and the fraction of
low values goes down
at night, right, which
is consistent with what
they saw as well.
There is another
way to measure it,
which is, instead of
using normal ranges,
the lab actually gives
you a call that says,
is this value
normal, low, or high?
And we can use that.
That's a little bit
more subtle because it
depends on calibration
of the equipment
and is updated as the
calibration changes.
So that's probably a
little bit more accurate.
But you see essentially
the same phenomenon here.
But if you look at the
distributions of when
measurements are done
that turn out to be normal
versus when they turn
out to be abnormal,
there is a lot of similarity
between the normal
and the abnormal curves of when
those measurements are taken.
So we're not seeing that.
OK, let me race
through to the end.
This is my heartbeat
from my watch.
You can actually
download the stuff
and put it in your
favorite analysis engine
and take a look.
So here I was running
across the Harvard bridge.
And if you look at my heart rate
variability over the 30 seconds
or so, you see that
the interbeat interval
ranges from about
550 to about 600
and whatever 20 milliseconds.
And so you could calculate
my heart rate variability,
which is thought to be an
indicator of heart health
and so on.
You can calculate
that I was running
at a pace of about 100--
my heart was beating at a pace
of about 100 beats per minute.
So you know there's all
sorts of information
like that available.
Now, as I said, I'm not
going to get into this today,
but this was a very
successful recently
published paper where
they're able to take
a look at images of the lung.
So this is a transverse
scan of the lung.
And they have a deep
learning machine
that is able to identify
these two yellow marked things
as pulmonary emboli as opposed
to these other things that
are just random
flecks in the tissue.
And I can't do that by eyeball.
Maybe a good radiologist
might be able to,
but this is claimed in
the paper to outperform
decent radiologists already.
This was one of
the articles that
led Geoff Hinton to make this
rather stupid pronouncement
that said, tell your children
not to become radiologists
because the profession will be
over by the time they get fully
trained, which I don't believe.
They may do different things,
but they won't go away.
This was a slide from Ron
Kikinis at the Brigham,
and they're using
automated techniques
of analyzing white
matter in order
to identify lupus lesions.
So lupus is a bad
disease that shows up
in these magnetic resonance
images in certain ways.
The last thing I want to
talk about today is notes.
So my students did a little
exercise last semester
where we tried to see how good
is the average ape, namely
member of my research group,
at predicting mortality?
And so we took a bunch of
cases from the MIMIC data
set, blinded to the question
of whether the person lived
or died.
We gave the data to people in
a kind of visualization tool,
sort of like the one that
I showed you earlier,
that summarizes the case, and
then also gave people access
to the notes, the deidentified
notes about those cases,
to see whether people could
predict, better than a coin
flip, whether somebody
was going to live or die.
And the answer is yes,
slightly better, OK?
Not immensely better
but slightly better.
And furthermore, it looks
like, by giving them feedback,
so as they're looking
at these cases
and trying to make
the prediction,
they make a prediction,
you tell them if they
were right or wrong, we learn.
And so we get slightly
better than slightly better
than random, right?
It's kind of interesting.
OK, so one of the
things I discovered
is that, at least
when I was playing
the monkey in this
exercise, I found the notes
to be immensely useful,
much more useful
than the trend lines
of laboratory data.
Partly, it's because I'm
used to reading English.
I'm not so used to reading
graphs of laboratory data.
But part of it is that there is
a level of human understanding
that is transmitted
in the nursing notes
and in the discharge summaries
and so on that you don't get
from just looking at raw data.
And so there is very
much the sense, which
we're going to talk about
in a couple of weeks,
of how can we take advantage
of that information,
extract it, and use it
in the kinds of modeling
that we want to do?
So in MIMIC, if
you look, we have
nursing notes, and
radiology reports,
and more nursing notes, and
electrocardiogram reports,
and doctor's notes, and
discharge summaries,
and echocardiograms,
respiratory, et cetera.
And if you look at
the distribution
of the lengths of these,
these are, unfortunately,
not on the same scale.
But the discharge
summary is the thing
that's written at the time
you leave the hospital.
So this is sort of the
summary of everything
that happened to you during
your hospitalization.
And it's long.
So, you know, it goes up
to like 30,000 characters.
You know, it's a short story,
not so short short story.
Nursing notes tend
to be shorter.
They run up to about
3,000 characters.
This other set of
nursing notes, which
I think comes from the other
system, is a little bit longer.
It goes up to about 5,000.
Doctor's notes are a
little bit longer yet.
They go up to about 10,000,
15,000 characters, typically.
And there are various
other kinds of notes.
So I just wanted to
show you a few of these.
Here's a brief nursing note.
So this is a patient who is
hypotensive but not in shock.
Patient remains
on this drug drip
at 0.75 micrograms per
kilogram per minute,
no titration needed
at this time.
Their blood pressure is
stable at more than 100.
Their mean arterial pressure
is 65, greater than 65.
Wean them from this drug
presumably if it's tolerated.
A wound infection, so
anterior groin area
open and oozing moderate amounts
of thin, pink-tinged serous
fluid.
Patient's stooling with small
amounts of stool on something
and dangerously close to
the open wound, et cetera.
So this is sort of
the nurse's snapshot.
She just went in,
saw the patient--
by the way, I say
she, but probably
a vast majority of nurses
in Boston area hospitals
really are women, but there
are some male nurses--
and will record sort
of a snapshot of what's
going on with the patient.
What are the concerns?
In principle, this is
going to be useful not only
as a part of the medical
record, but also when
this nurse goes off shift and
the next nurse comes on shift.
Then this is a recording of
what the state of the patient
was the last time they
were seen by the nurse.
In reality, the nurses tend
to tell each other verbally
rather than relying on
the written version.
I remember one time talking to
a nurse in an intensive care
unit in another part of
the country, and I said,
so whoever reads
your notes, and she
says, quality assurance
officers, so the hospital has
people responsible
for trying to assess
the quality of care
they're giving,
and lawyers when
there's a lawsuit.
And she was very happy because
she had saved the hospital
10 million dollars by
having carefully recorded
that some procedure had been
done to a patient who then
had a bad outcome and was suing
the hospital for their neglect
in not having done this.
But because it was
in the note, that
was proof that it
actually had been done,
and therefore the
hospital wasn't liable.
But there is a lot of
information in here.
Now, I'm going to show you many
pages of a typical discharge
summary.
So this is somebody
on the surgery service
who came in complaining
of leg pain, redness,
and swelling
secondary to infection
of the left femoral
popliteal bypass.
So she had surgery--
I think she.
Yeah, female.
She had surgery which
didn't heal well,
so major surgical or
invasive procedure, incision
and drainage and pulse
irrigation of the left groin,
and left above-knee popliteal
site incisions with exploration
of bypass graft, and excision of
the entire left common femoral
artery to above-knee blah,
blah, blah, blah blah, blah.
So this is what they did.
History of the present illness--
she's a 45-year-old
woman who underwent
the left femoral, a.k.a.
doctor something or other
with PTFE, whatever that
is, over a month ago
on a certain date.
By the way, these
bracketed asterisked things
are where we've taken out
identifying information
from the record.
She had been doing
well post-operatively
and was seen in the clinic six
days prior to presentation.
At this time, she acutely
developed nausea, vomiting,
fevers, and progressive
redness, swelling,
pain of her left
thigh, et cetera, OK?
So that's just page
one of many pages.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Just a question.
Is this completely [INAUDIBLE]
information [INAUDIBLE]
patient's name or date?
PROFESSOR: Not in this system.
There are people--
Henry Chueh at
Mass General spent
10 years building a system that
had autocomplete and so on.
And some doctors liked it
and some doctors hated it.
And the MGH threw out
all of their old systems
in order to buy Epic,
and so it's gone.
It was like 10 years
of work down the drain.
But it was not a
spectacular success.
Because whenever you
have auto complete,
you have to anticipate
every possible answer.
And people are very
creative, and they always
want to type something
that you didn't anticipate.
So it's hard to support it.
AUDIENCE: What is Epic?
That's like the new--
PROFESSOR: Epic is
a big company that
has been winning all the
recent contests for installing
electronic medical
record systems.
Remember in my last
lecture, I showed that we're
reaching about 100% saturation?
So they've been winning a lot
of the installation deals.
And they're getting
a lot of the subsidy.
The estimate I heard was that
Partners Healthcare, which
is MGH at the Brigham and a
couple of other hospitals,
spent somewhere on the
order of two billion dollars
installing the system.
So that included all
the customizations
and all the training and
all the administrative stuff
that went with it.
But that's a huge
amount of money.
AUDIENCE: I agree.
PROFESSOR: OK, so we have
past medical history--
pack a day smoker,
abused cocaine
but says she stopped
six months ago,
has asthma, type 2 diabetes.
Social history, family history.
These are of the
physical exam results.
So it's giving you a lot of
information about the person.
Description of the wound
down at the bottom.
Pertinent lab results.
So these are copied out
of the laboratory tables.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Just to double
check with the drug results--
PROFESSOR: Sorry?
AUDIENCE: Just to double
check with the drug results
two slides back--
PROFESSOR: Yeah
AUDIENCE: It said-- so it
has the fake dates of 2190
up there.
PROFESSOR: Yep.
AUDIENCE: So the fact that there
was a positive test in 2187
would mean a year ago.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So that's
the medication.
PROFESSOR: Yeah, the
deindenfication technology here
maintains the relative dates
but not the absolute dates.
So these are results,
again, copied out
of the laboratory database
into the discharge summary.
Brief hospital course, and
then a review of systems,
so what's going on
neurologically, cardiovascular,
pulmonary, GI, GU, et cetera.
Infectious disease, endocrine,
hematology, prophylaxis.
And at the time was
discharged, the patient
was doing well, no fever
and stable vital signs,
tolerating a regular
diet, ambulating, voiding
without assistance, and
pain was well controlled.
Medications on
admission, so this
was the medication
reconciliation.
Discharge medication, so this is
what she's being sent home on.
Discharge disposition
is to the home with some
follow up service,
and she's going home.
And the discharge
diagnosis is infected
left femoral popliteal bypass
graft and the condition.
And these are the instructions
to the patient that say, you
know, here's what you can
do, here is when you should
come back and tell us if
something is going wrong,
et cetera.
And here's what you should
report if it happens.
You know, if you have sudden
severe bleeding or swelling,
do this.
Follow up with doctor
somebody or other.
Call his clinic at this number
to schedule an appointment
and then follow up with doctor
somebody else in two weeks.
I think this is the same one.
So just a couple of final
words about standards.
So you saw in David's
introductory lecture
a reference to Odyssey, which
is a standard method of encoding
the kind of data that
we're talking about today.
There is a likelihood that
the next release of the MIMIC
database will adopt the Odyssey
formats rather than the--
yeah.
David's shaking his
head, wondering why.
Me, too.
AUDIENCE: Odyssey hasn't handled
clinical notes very well yet.
PROFESSOR: Well, so, you
know, what always happens,
as you say, I'm going to
adopt the standard asterisk
with the following extensions.
And that's probably
what's going to happen.
But it means that the
central tables, you
know, the ICD-9 code tables and
the drug tables, some things
like that, are likely to
wind up adopting the formats
of the Odyssey database.
You should also know about this
thing called FHIR, F-H-I-R,
the Fast Health
Interoperability Resources.
So HL7 is the
standards organization
that had a tremendous
success in the early 1990s
in solving the problem of how
to allow laboratories to report
lab data back to the
hospitals or the clinics that
ordered the labs.
And that character
string with the up arrows
and the vertical bars and
so on that I showed you
before that had LOINK encoded
in it is that standard.
That's called HL7 Version 2.
It's still in use very widely,
they then got ambitious
and suffered second
system syndrome, which
is they decided to
build HL7 Version 3,
which I used to teach in
a class here 10 years ago.
But one of my friends who
works for a company that
helps hospitals implement that
sent me a 38 megabyte PDF file
that describes what you
need to know in order
to implement that system.
And as a result,
nobody was doing it.
So FHIR is a gross
simplification
of that that starts
off and says,
if a doctor refers a
new patient to you,
what is the minimum set of data
that you need to know in order
to take care of that person?
And FHIR tries to provide just
that subset of all of the data.
It has become a standard mainly
because, after Congress spent
$42 billion dollars
or so bribing people
into buying these
information systems,
they got mad that the
information systems they bought
couldn't talk to each other.
And so they called in,
on the carpet, the heads
of these IT companies,
health IT companies,
and they yelled at
them and they made
them promise that there
would be interoperability.
They promised.
And out of that came FHIR.
It was probably simultaneously
developed but they adopted it.
And so now, in principle,
it's possible to exchange
data between different
hospitals, at least
to the level of that degree
of harmonization of the data.
In reality, the
companies don't want
you to do that because they
like there to be friction
in not being able to
take all your data
to a different hospital, because
it is more likely to leave you
at the one that you're at.
So there is complicated
socioeconomic kinds
of issues in all this.
But at least the standard exists
and is becoming more and more
widely deployed as long as
Congress pays attention.
It's ugly.
So here is what a patient
looks like, right?
It's the usual
unreadable XML garbage.
But fortunately,
there are parsers
that can turn it into JSON
and simpler representations.
And so that's pretty common.
So the terminologies that exist
are LOINK, NBC, ICD-9 and 10.
SNOMED I didn't
talk about today.
DSM-5 is the Diagnostic
and Statistical
Manual for Psychiatrists.
That's used as a
common coding method
for describing
psychiatric disease.
And there are many
more of these.
There's something called
the Unified Medical Language
Systems Metathesaurus from the
National Library of Medicine
that integrates about 180 of
these different terminologies.
And so there is a
nice one-stop shop
where you can get all
these things from them.
So takeaway lessons,
know your data.
Remember that first example
of the heart rates, that
comes up over and over again.
And doing machine learning
and analysis on data
that you don't understand
is likely to lead you
to false conclusions.
Harmonization is difficult
and time consuming.
And there are lots of
things for which we just
don't have standards,
and so everybody develops
their own representations.
I had a PhD student about a
decade ago who, in his thesis,
wrote that he spent about
half his time cleaning data.
And I gave that thesis
to another student who
started a few years
later who read it,
and he comes to me just
awestruck and he says, what?
He only spent half
his time cleaning?
Unfortunately, that's roughly
where we are in this field.
So sorry to be a
downer, but that's
the current state of the art.
And next time, David will start
by looking at actually building
some models with
these kinds of data
and showing you what
we can accomplish.
Thank you.